Guide to the Kirkridge Retreat and Study Center Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Kirkridge Retreat and Study Center records
1942-2007
RG 261
Yale University Divinity School Library
3.75
(7 boxes)
These are the official archives of Kirkridge Retreat and Study Center in Bangor, PA. Kirkridge is an ecumenical Christian center founded by John Oliver Nelson, who was influenced by George MacLeod's work with the Iona Community. Nelson was a professor of Christian vocation and director of field work at Yale Divinity School from 1950 to 1964.
Kirkridge Retreat and Study Center
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kirkridge Retreat and Study Center, 2014
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Biographical / Historical
KIRKRIDGE RETREAT CENTER 1942 – 2008
The Mission Statement of the Center is: "Kirkridge is a retreat and study center rooted in Christ close to the earth, where people from diverse backgrounds find community and experience the transforming power of the spirit for personal wholeness, reconciliation and justice in the world."
Kirkridge was founded in 1942 by John Oliver Nelson, a Presbyterian minister who was professor of Christian vocation and director of field work at Yale Divinity School from 1950 to 1964. Nelson visited the island of Iona in Scotland in 1938 and was influenced by what he found there – a community of trainee ministers and craftsmen sharing the task of reconstructing the buildings attached to the recently rebuilt Abbey. In addition to living together as a community they shared the work of laboring and the daily worship. The purpose was to prepare trainee Church of Scotland ministers for work in deprived urban areas in Glasgow and elsewhere.
John Oliver Nelson, inspired by what he had seen on Iona, worked with a few other Presbyterian ministers to find a suitable location in the United States to found a center on similar lines. He purchased a property in the Pocono mountains, which he named Kirkridge.The initial aim of the group was to develop suitable training for trainee Presbyterian ministers to equip them for ministry in deprived urban and rural areas. The Kirkridge emphasis from the beginning was the integration of contemplation and action for justice. The vision is encapsulated in the theme "picket and pray" – i.e., being engaged in "picketing" – social activist work for racial, gender, sexual, political economic religious justice in the world and also in "praying" – spiritual development, personal healing. The vision spread to laity and clergy from wide denominational roots and also to the idea that members of congregations should attend retreats with their pastor.
Work retreats were the first form of retreat held at Kirkridge. For participants this meant manual work – cutting down trees, digging, painting etc, common worship,corporate silence, discussion and Bible study in community. Over the next few decades retreats were introduced for women's groups and for men's groups.There were retreats to which undergraduates from different seminaries were invited to attend to consider unconventional ministries in slums, industrial areas, or rural areas of special sociological concern – they were called the Square Pegs. They continued to meet for at least 20 years. There were retreats led by Gordon Cosby, Robert Raines, Gerald Jud who began the Shalom retreats, Bishop John Spong, Bishop John Robinson and George MacLeod the founder of the Iona Community.
In 1969 there were two brave new experiments which were ultimately unsuccessful – a new alcoholic rehabilitation center was opened offering a minimum stay of 28 days.This was not intended to and did not replace the retreats for recovering alcoholics. In addition, a school was opened in the September of 1969. it contained 20 boys and 16 girls of grades 10 and 11 who were housed with a faculty of 8; it existed for two years.
In 1983 the first pilgrimage went over to Iona, the inspiration behind John Oliver Nelson's concept of Kirkridge. There have been a number of Iona pilgrimages since. In the 1980s and 90s retreats were introduced on the following subjects: recovery for adult children of alcoholics and families dealing with all kinds of addiction; personal and spiritual growth; retreats for men and retreats for women; retreats for the victims of sexual abuse; retreats led by Parker Palmer. There were also retreats on Jewish and Islamic spirituality; on creation spirituality and ecological justice; and increasing numbers of poets, writers and artists came to lead retreats.
By 1990 nearly 2500 from 89 groups and organizations had made use of the Kirkridge facilities. In addition during 1990 a total of 132 people made private retreats there. From 1996 Kirkridge entered into partnerships with other group, including the Fellowship of Reconciliation, the Sojourners, the Center for sexuality and religion and Drew Theological Seminary. Kirkridge also entered into discussions during this period with institutions tackling such issues as: the abolition of the death penalty; total nuclear disarmament; proactively promoting racial justice; developing a global feminist spirituality and making pastors more aware of a broad range of human sexuality issues.
Peacemaking has always held a special place at Kirkridge. The Peacemaker Training Institute of the Fellowship of Reconciliation, which had first been co-sponsored by Kirkridge in 1952, was renewed in 1995. Daniel Berrigan held a number of retreats at the center. A series of international peace pilgrimmages was also introduced, with visits to Taize in France in 1998, to Cuba in 1997 and 1999, and the Holy Land in 1998, as well as to Iona on a three-yearly basis from 1983.
John Oliver Nelson became director of the Center in 1964, after the retirement of the first residential secretaries, Edith and Joe Platt. Nelson stood down in 1974 and Robert Raines, pastor of a church in Ohio, and already well known at Kirkridge was appointed in his stead. In 1994 Robert Raines retired as director and he was replaced by Cynthia Crowner. The Center continued to offer a rich variety of retreats including retreats for Gay and Lesbian groups, the Community of Sisters and peace groups – retreats on subjects such as spirituality, Biblical interpretation, music, art. In 2005 Jean Richardson became director of the Center and the above themes have continued. In addition she has developed retreats on Circles of Trust (introduced by the Center for Courage and Renewal set up by Parker Palmer).
As the years passed the Farmhouse was added to and there are now 5 properties which form part of the retreat center - The Lodge,Turning Point, and Hermitage,all used for retreats and Skye, Quiet Ways and Van der Bent House which are used for accommodation for staff or guests.
Scope and Contents
The Kirkridge Retreat and Study Center records have been maintained in the order in which they were received. The records document the formation of the center, its program activities, publications, physical campus, and related groups. Materials designated with an asterisk are still in the possession of the Kirkridge Center and will be transferred to the archives shortly.
Arrangement
I. Administrative and Strategic Policy Records
II. Programme Documentation
III. Newsletters and Pamphlets
IV. Kirkridge Publications
V. Drawings and Plans
VI. Creation of Kirkridge and Related Documents
VII. Specific Groups Linked to Kirkridge
Religious institutions; Nelson, John Oliver, 1909-1990; Kirkridge Retreat and Study Center
- Administrative and Strategic Policy Records, Series I
  - Minutes of Board / Committee meetings, 1943-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of Board / Committee meetings, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of Board / Committee meetings, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes of Board / Committee meetings, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes of Board / Committee meetings, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes of Board / Committee meetings*, 1991-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes of Board / Committee meetings*, 2000-2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board members, 1951-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Council members, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Visions and plans, 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Visions and plans, 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Visions and plans, 1990s-2008 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Kirkridge school - Minutes of meeting of minutes, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence between the resident secretaries and John Casteel Programme chairman and Board members, 1947-1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 50th Anniversary celebrations, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lilly Foundation grants, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Theological education grants, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Programme Documentation, Series II
  - Retreat programme, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Retreat programme, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Retreat programme, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Retreat programme, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Retreat programme, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Retreat programme, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Retreat programme, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Retreat programme, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Retreat programme, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Retreat programme, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Retreat programme, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Retreat programme, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Retreat programme, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Retreat programme, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Retreat programme, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Retreat programme (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Retreat programme, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Retreat programme, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Retreat programme, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Retreat programme, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Retreat programme, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Retreat programme, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Retreat programme, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Retreat programme, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Retreat programme, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Programme catalogue, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Programme catalogue, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Programme catalogue, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Programme catalogue, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Programme catalogue, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Programme catalogue, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Programme catalogue, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Programme catalogue, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Programme catalogue, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Programme catalogue, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Programme catalogue*, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Programme catalogue*, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Programme catalogue*, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Programme catalogue*, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Programme catalogue*, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Programme catalogue*, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Programme catalogue*, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Programme catalogue*, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Programme catalogue*, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Programme catalogue*, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Programme catalogue*, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Programme catalogue*, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Programme catalogue*, 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 68)
- Newsletters and Pamphlets, Series III
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Contour, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Contour, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Contour, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Contour, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Contour, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Contour, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Contour, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 2002 (Box 4)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Ridgeleaf and Contour, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Mountainside notes beginnings of quiet ways, 1947-1970 (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Beginnings of quiet ways, 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Notes on early days at Kirkridge, Undated (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Historical summary of Kirkridge by John Oliver Nelson, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - An experiment for the future*, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Letters from Joe and Edith Platt to Kirkridge friends, 1953-1963 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Newspaper cuttings, 1944-1992 (Box 4, Folder 138)
- Kirkridge Publications, Series IV
  - Because we are one - Songs for worship, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 139)
  - The Sycammore book - Liturgies and prayers, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 140)
  - Pilgrimage around the mountain, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 141)
  - Seasons of worship at Kirkridge, 2007 (Box 5)
  - Kirkridge Kookery, The Kirkridge Cookbook, 1976,1993 (Box 5, Folder 143)
  - Renewed intention Kirkridge thus far, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - You're alright Jack, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 145)
  - Go Tell It on the Mountain, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - The legacy continues, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 147)
- Drawings and Plans, Series V
  - Plans of Kirkridge gardens, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 148)
  - Plans of Tran, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 149)
  - Trails maps, Undated (Box 5, Folder 150)
  - Memorial garden and benches, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 151)
  - Kirkridge celtic cross, Undated (Box 5, Folder 152)
  - Stained glass window turning point, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 153)
  - Calligraphy of rune of hospitality, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 154)
  - Miscellaneous art work, Undated (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - Drawings and plans of Kirkridge, Undated (Box 5, Folder 156, Box OV1)
  - Photographs of board members and retreat leaders, Undated (Box 5, Folder 156)
- Creation of Kirkridge and Related Documents, Series VI
  - Correspondence about setting up a retreat center, 1942-1943 (Box 5)
  - Four preliminary papers, 1942-1943 (Box 5)
  - The Kirkridge discipline, 1949-1961 (Box 5, Folder 159)
  - Style of Life and Readings, 1962-1978 (Box 5, Folder 160)
  - Readings and Intentions, 1981-2005 (Box 5, Folder 161)
  - Records of members "Who followed the Rules" and correspondence with them, 1944-1957 (Box 6, Folder 162)
  - Report forms on the discipline, 1940s-1950s (Box 6, Folder 163)
  - Link with the Iona Community - correspondence between George Macleod and John Nelson: correspondence on various issues,the discipline, publishing, articles group led by John nelson to Iona, 1946-1959, various1983 (Box 6, Folder 164)
  - Iona - correspondence, Various (Box 6, Folder 165)
  - Iona group visit led by Jon, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 166)
- Specific Groups Linked to Kirkridge, Series VII
  - Company at Kirkridge (inauguration), 1976 (Box 6, Folder 167)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 168)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 169)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 170)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 171)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 172)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 173)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 174)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 175)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 176)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 177)
  - Company at Kirkridge, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 178)
  - Square Peg retreats, 1950s (Box 6, Folder 179)
  - Square Peg retreats, 1960s (Box 6, Folder 180)
  - Square Peg retreats, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 181)
  - Relationship retreat, 1970-1980 (Box 6, Folder 182)
  - Covenanters, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 183)
  - Shalom retreats, 1970s (Box 6, Folder 184)
  - The K. Group, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 185)
  - Log book signed with commentary by visitors to Kirkridge, Various (Box 7, Folder 186)